<?xml version="1.0"?>
<worksheet>
            <Row>
                <Cell><Data ss:Type="String">Boater Certification Laws</Data></Cell>
                <Cell ss:StyleID="s62"><Data ss:Type="String">In Canada, ALL operators of recreational powered watercraft must have proof of operator competency in order to operate any vessel. Proof of competency must be carried onboard the pleasure craft at all times while operating the craft. Failure to carry proof of competency can result in harsh monetary fines, which may be issued by any officer of the peace. Note: &quot;operate&quot; refers to the act of controlling the speed and course of a pleasure craft. PCOC Proof of competency can be a Pleasure Craft Operator Card, a Boating Safety Course Completion Card, a rental boat safety checklist, proof of successful completion of a boating safety course, or a training certificate recognized by Transport Canada. If carrying a Pleasure Craft Operator Card as proof of competency, the original card must be carried on board. Photocopies or other copies of the card will not be accepted as proof of competency. In the case of non-residents of Canada, they are required to have proof of operator competency if they operate their pleasure craft on Canadian waters for more than 44 consecutive days, or if they are operating a pleasure craft that is registered or licensed in Canada. An operator card that meets requirements in the non-resident’s home state or country will be recognized as valid proof of competency in Canada. Note: For more information on additional proofs of competency that are recognized by Transport Canada, please visit www.boatingsafety.gc.ca, or call the Boating Safety Infoline at 1-800-267-6687.</Data></Cell>
            </Row>
            <Row>
                <Cell><Data ss:Type="String">Age Restrictions</Data></Cell>
                <Cell ss:StyleID="s62"><Data ss:Type="String">Please take note of the following age restrictions: Children under 12 years of age may only operate a boat with a motor of up to 10 hp, unless accompanied and directly supervised by someone 16 years of age or older. Persons 12 to 15 years of age may only operate a boat with a motor of up to 40 hp, unless accompanied and directly supervised by someone 16 years of age or older. The minimum age for operating a personal watercraft (i.e., Sea-Doo®, Jet Ski®) is 16 years of age. Small-vessel safety equipment and safety precaution requirements for boaters include a “careless operation of a vessel” offence, which requires boaters to travel safely and avoid putting themselves and others at risk. Card Note: A Pleasure Craft is defined as a boat, a ship, a vessel, or any other description of water craft that is used exclusively for pleasure and does not carry passengers or goods for hire, reward, remuneration or any object of profit.</Data></Cell>
            </Row>
</worksheet>
     