<?xml version="1.0"?>
<Worksheet>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Boater Certification Laws</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>In Canada, ALL operators of recreational powered watercraft must have proof of operator competency in order to operate any vessel. Proof of competency must be carried onboard the pleasure craft at all times while operating the craft. Failure to carry proof of competency can result in harsh monetary fines, which may be issued by any officer of the peace.&#13;Note: &quot;operate&quot; refers to the act of controlling the speed and course of a pleasure craft.&#13;PCOC&#13;Proof of competency can be a Pleasure Craft Operator Card, a Boating Safety Course Completion Card, a rental boat safety checklist, proof of successful completion of a boating safety course, or a training certificate recognized by Transport Canada.&#13;If carrying a Pleasure Craft Operator Card as proof of competency, the original card must be carried on board. Photocopies or other copies of the card will not be accepted as proof of competency.&#13;In the case of non-residents of Canada, they are required to have proof of operator competency if they operate their pleasure craft on Canadian waters for more than 44 consecutive days, or if they are operating a pleasure craft that is registered or licensed in Canada. An operator card that meets requirements in the non-resident’s home state or country will be recognized as valid proof of competency in Canada.&#13;Note: For more information on additional proofs of competency that are recognized by Transport Canada, please visit www.boatingsafety.gc.ca, or call the Boating Safety Infoline at 1-800-267-6687.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>bcl.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Age Restrictions</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Please take note of the following age restrictions:&#13;Children under 12 years of age may only operate a boat with a motor of up to 10 hp, unless accompanied and directly supervised by someone 16 years of age or older.&#13;Persons 12 to 15 years of age may only operate a boat with a motor of up to 40 hp, unless accompanied and directly supervised by someone 16 years of age or older.&#13;The minimum age for operating a personal watercraft (i.e., Sea-Doo®, Jet Ski®) is 16 years of age.&#13;Small-vessel safety equipment and safety precaution requirements for boaters include a “careless operation of a vessel” offence, which requires boaters to travel safely and avoid putting themselves and others at risk.&#13;Card&#13;Note: A Pleasure Craft is defined as a boat, a ship, a vessel, or any other description of water craft that is used exclusively for pleasure and does not carry passengers or goods for hire, reward, remuneration or any object of profit.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Know Before You Go</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Avoid danger on the water by taking a few minutes before you leave to check the following:&#13;Weather forecast;&#13;Local hazards;&#13;Maps and charts;&#13;Your onboard PFDs;&#13;First-aid kit, tool kit, tools and spare parts onboard;&#13;Sufficient fuel;&#13;Safety equipment in working order; and&#13;Ensure that someone knows where you are going and when to expect you back.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Wear Your Life Jacket or Personal Flotation Device</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>The major cause of fatalities involving small boats is drowning from falls overboard, which is why it is important for boaters to wear their life jacket or personal flotation device at all times. In fact, research indicates that fewer than 15% of all drowning victims were wearing a life jacket or PFD at the time of death. However, less than half of all who wear a PFD wear it properly. All boaters should wear PFDs when in and around water, not just when operating or riding in a vessel.&#13;Know Before You Go&#13;Note: A &quot;vessel&quot; is defined as any type of watercraft, including non-displacement craft and seaplanes used or capable of being used as a means of transportation on water.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>life-jacket.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Boat Sober!</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Don’t drink and drive—this applies just as much to operating a boat as it does to operating a motor vehicle. Although the number of reported impaired boat operators is decreasing, alcohol use is still a major factor in more than 40% of all preventable water-related fatalities, and over half of all power boating accidents.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>sober.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Drive Your Powerboat or Personal Watercraft Responsibly</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Capsizing, collisions and falls overboard are all leading causes of boating-related fatalities. Look before you act, sit low in the boat, drive at a moderate speed, and be aware of changing weather conditions as well as the time of day. Never overload your boat and always respect the Canadian Compliance Notice label for small boats.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Bring Your Marine Global Positioning System (GPS) or Nautical Charts (marine charts)&#13;</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Increasing in popularity over the past few years, GPS devices can be extremely helpful while on the water; however a GPS is a mechanical device and can fail. Having the appropriate nautical charts (also known as marine charts) onboard are also a great asset, and should be available in case the GPS does not work properly. This is especially important when boating on unfamiliar waterways.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>compass.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Boat Terminology</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Specific terms are used to describe the various parts of a boat; each end and side of the boat, its length and width, and its accessories all have specific terms. Every boater should be familiar with the following terms before operating a boat.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>boat.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Additional Terminology</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Here are some additional terms that boaters should be familiar with before operating a boat:&#13; &#13;Aft - Located near or at the stern of the boat;&#13;Beam - The width of a boat at the widest point;&#13;Bilge - The lowest point of a boat’s interior hull;&#13;Draft - The vertical distance from the waterline to the lowest point of the keel; the minimum depth of water in which a vessel will float;&#13;Forward - Located near, or at, the bow of the boat;&#13;Freeboard - The vertical distance from the waterline to the gunwale;&#13;Keel - The main structural member of a boat comprising its backbone plus the lateral area beneath the hull, helping to provide stability and reduce the sideways drift of a boat;&#13;Wake - The disturbed column of water around and behind a moving vessel which is set into motion&#13;by the passage of a vessel; and&#13;Waterline - The intersection of a boat’s hull and the water‘s surface.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>boat-front.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Boat Hull Designs and Uses</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Boat bottoms or hulls are available in a variety of shapes and sizes. Each hull type is designed either to displace or plane through the water. Sailing vessels and large cruise ships use displacement hulls because the combination of their size and power will not allow them to plane. On the other hand, smaller powerboats are typically built with planing hulls that are designed to rise up and ride on top of the water at higher speeds than displacement hull boats.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Hull Types</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Personal watercraft designs generally consist of the following hull types: Flat Bottom, Round Bottom, Deep-V Hull, Multi-hull.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Flat Bottom Hulls</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Great for fishing, and are generally designed for slow speeds and calm water.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>FlatBottomHulls.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Round Bottom</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>While these boats, such as canoes, move smoothly through the water with little effort, boaters must be cautious when loading, entering and exiting boats with this type of hull because they roll very easily.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>RoundBottom.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Deep-V Hull</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>This is the most common hull type for powerboats, it moves through rough water at higher speeds and give a smoother ride than flat-bottom or round-bottom boats. It also requires a larger engine than other boats.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>DeepVHull.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Multi-hull</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>The most stable of the hull types, these boats require plenty of room to steer and turn. Catamarans and pontoon boats use the multi-hull design.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Multi-hull.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Engine types</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Outboard - This type of engine is mounted outside of the boat, usually on its transom. It is steered, or controlled, by either a hand tiller or a steering wheel that will cause the entire engine to move when the steering is adjusted.&#13;Inboard - Inboard engines are typically four-stroke automotive engines which are modified for use on the water. An inboard engine is mounted inside the hull of the boat and powers the drive shaft which is connected to a propeller. When the steering wheel of an inboard engine is manipulated, it moves a rudder that is positioned directly behind the propeller.&#13;Sterndrives - Stern drives are often called &lt;inboard / outboards&gt; because they have features found on both inboard and outboard engines. Similar to inboards, stern drives use four-stroke automotive engines that are modified for use on the water. They are mounted inside the boat and attached through the transom, they power the drive shaft which is connected to the propeller. When the steering wheel used to control the stern drive engine is adjusted it changes the direction of the propeller.&#13;In the past, outboards were typically two-stroke engines, but manufacturers have since switched to four-stroke engines. Two-stroke engines require oil to be mixed with gasoline to lubricate the engine and four-stroke engines require the oil and gasoline to be separate. Four-stroke engines, in addition to running more quietly and smoothly, are more environmentally friendly because their exhaust is virtually smokeless compared to two-strokes.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Enginetypes.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Compliance Notice and Permit Requirements</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Compliance Notice&#13;All pleasure craft under 24m in length that are motorized or designed to be motorized, must have a compliance notice. For vessels less than 6m in length, the compliance notice indicates the maximum gross load to be carried, including but not limited to the total weight of all persons, fuel, and any equipment onboard.&#13;The compliance notice for vessels of 6m or less should indicate the &quot;maximum recommended safe limits for motor power&quot; for the hull. This limit must never be surpassed. This calculation is based on the gross load capacity of the vessel powered by an outboard motor only.&#13;As owner or operator of a vessel, you must be aware of the gross load capacity that the hull can safely transport, during fair weather. Remember that a loaded boat is more prone to swamping, and that chances of swamping or capsizing can be decreased by reducing your load in poor weather or rough water.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>ComplianceNotice.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Pleasure Craft Licences</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>A pleasure craft licence refers to the set of identification numbers to be displayed on both sides of your boat's bow. All pleasure craft principally maintained or operated in Canada propelled by motors of 10 horsepower (7.5 kW) or greater must be licenced. This includes personal watercraft. Alternatively to licensing your boat, you can register it with Transport Canada.&#13;It is the responsibility of the person owning or operating the pleasure craft to ensure that the licence is onboard and available upon request by an enforcement officer. There are no fees to obtain a pleasure craft licence.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Hull Identification Number</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>According to the Canada Shipping Act 2001, all pleasure craft (with OR without a motor) manufactured in or imported into Canada after August 1, 1981, must be permanently marked with a Hull Identification Number (HIN). This 12-character serial number is often used to help identify lost or stolen vessels. If you are purchasing a vessel, it is important to make sure that it has a HIN. It is illegal to alter or otherwise tamper with a Hull Identification Number</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Hull Identification.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Pleasure Craft Licence is not a Registration</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Vessel registration is the title of ownership of a boat or vessel, which includes the official vessel name and the name of the owner(s). Although not required for pleasure craft, they can be registered on a voluntary basis at the owner's discretion. Registration is valid for three years and fees vary depending on the type of vessel and type of registration. For more information, please consult with Transport Canada's Vessel Registry at www.tc.gc.ca</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Change in Name or Address</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Pleasure craft licenses are valid for a period of 10 years. If the owner's name or address changes, the licence must be updated with the Pleasure Craft Licensing Centre. The pleasure craft may be operated without an accurate name and/or date on the license for up to 90 days, as long as documents are carried onboard that confirm the change and the date of change. Applications for licence updates are available from the Pleasure Craft Licensing Centre online at www.boatingsafety.gc.ca or for pickup in person through your local Service Canada Centre.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Transferring your Licence</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>If the ownership of a licensed pleasure craft is transferred, the former owner must sign the transfer form that is printed on the reverse side of the licence and deliver it to the new owner. The new owner will then be required to submit an application form along with the required documentation by mail to The Pleasure Craft Licensing Centre to transfer the pleasure craft licence. The pleasure craft can be operated for a maximum of 90 days without a license, as long as the new owner has applied for a license and carries proof of name and address onboard. For more information on the sale or transfer of a pleasure craft licence, visit the Office of Boating Safety or call the Boating Safety InfoLine at 1-800-267-6687.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell/>
    </Row>
    <Row>
        <Cell><Data>Display your Licence Number</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Display your Licence Number&#13;All licensed vessels must display the licence number in block letters that are at least 7.5 centimetres (3 inches) in height.&#13;The licence number must also:&#13;Be displayed on both sides of the vessel’s bow and;&#13;Be in contrast with the colour of the background.&#13;For more information on pleasure craft licenses, please consult the Small Vessel Regulations under the Canada Shipping Act.</Data></Cell>
        <Cell><Data>Display your Licence Number.png</Data></Cell>
    </Row>
</Worksheet>
